<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lectures of Samuel Bird of Ipswidge vpon the 8. and 9. chapters of the second Epistle to the Corinthians</title>
            <author>Bird, Samuel, d. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855477</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855477</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16164)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 411:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lectures of Samuel Bird of Ipswidge vpon the 8. and 9. chapters of the second Epistle to the Corinthians</title>
                  <author>Bird, Samuel, d. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legate, Printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at top, affecting pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:1"/>
            <p>THE LECTVRES OF SAMVEL BIRD OF IPSWIDGE VPON the 8. and 9. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ters of the ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi> to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>rinthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by Iohn Legate, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ter to the Vniverſitie</hi> of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1598</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Legate, a compartment featuring heads, flowers and cornucopias, with the Royal Arms at the top, and four other blazons or coats of arms below (similar to McKerrow 185, with different crests)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE VVORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">is</hi>. MOORE AT TAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>mage Hall in Briſet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He motherly affection that you haue borne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes many, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes my ſelfe (good M<hi rend="sup">is</hi>. Moore) puts me out of all doubt, that this ſpeach of bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and liberalitie ſhal finde good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement at your hands. And I the more willingly commend theſe my labours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, becauſe of the bleſſed memorie of your good husband M. Moore, vnto whoſe doings the Lord hath ſet a moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſeale, by that bleſsing wherewith he hath bleſſed your children. For whereas commonly the kindred, eſpecially the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are woont to coole the liberalitie of bountifull perſons, yet it hath pleaſed God ſo to bleſſe your children, that they haue
<pb facs="tcp:20972:3"/> rather ſtrengthened your handes in this worke. This ſpeach may perhaps ſeeme to ſome to haue ſome cunning in it. But bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing priuie to my ſelfe of my ſimplicitie in this matter, and knowing that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth for the like reſpect make an open proclamation to all the world of the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulnes of the Macedonian Churches, I haue thereby beene encouraged to ſay as I haue ſaid. Thus deſiring the Lord to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then you in euery good dutie, and nothing doubting but that the God of all mercie which hath promiſed to ſhew mercie to the mercifull, will moſt aſſuredly comfort you in any diſtreſſe of ſicknes, or any other trouble that your old yeares may bring in vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, eſpecially at the great day, 2. Tim. 1. 18. with thankes for all your friendſhip, I heartily wiſh you well to fare in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>1597. Decemb. 16.</date>
               <signed>Samuel Bird.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO the ende, good Chriſtian Reader, thou mightest ſee the ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and the great varietie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which the Apoſtle doth vſe in this treatiſe of liberalitie and beuntifulnes, I thought it good firſt of all to Epitomiſe and to anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe theſe two chapters: and as it were in a glaſſe firſt generally to ſet them before thine eyes, before I come to the particular handling of them. For how ſoeuer coloured and rhetoricall brauerie as paintings looſe their grace, vnleſſe they be looked vpon a fare off: for after the ſound of them, if a man would call to minde what is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that which he hath heard, if a man in this manner ſhall come any thing neare to take a good view and ſurvay of any ſuch ſpeach, and ſhall looke vpon the ioynts of it, the force thereof is gone. On the other ſide toward ſound arguments the nearer that a man approcheth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the more migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:20972:4"/> are they to allure the beholder to a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them. The ſecond ſight of them plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a man better then the firſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <bibl>2. Corinth. chap. 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. Firſt therefore the Apoſtle doth mooue the Corinthians from the great worke and grace of God beſtowed vpon the Macedonian Churches.</p>
               <p>2 Who notwithſtanding they were in affliction and in great pouertie, in which kinde of eſtate men commonly thinke that they are to be borne withall though they doe not thinke vpon the poore eſtate of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, yet euen in this poore eſtate they releeued their brethren.</p>
               <p>3 And that more then their eſtate with eaſe could beare.</p>
               <p>4 Neither did they tarrie vntill they were haled thereunto by the perſwaſion of other men: but of their owne accord they offered, and that with great intreatie that their reliefe for theſe poore men, who notwithſtanding their diuers infirmities,
<pb facs="tcp:20972:4"/> were yet the Saints of God, vpon whome all our delight ſhould be ſet. They deſired therefore that their reliefe for them might be receiued.</p>
               <p>5 Thus was their bountifulnes euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our exſpectation, neither were they thus liberall to be fauoured by the vertue thereof in ſome corruption, as ſome haue beene, which would giue riuers of oyle that they might be diſpenſed withall in their ſinnes. But they reſigned euen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the will of God.</p>
               <p>6 Neither did they content themſelues with that that they were hardly able to giue, but they mooued others alſo to doe this dutie.</p>
               <p>7 Wherefore, Oye Corinthians, to the intent that no diſgrace may ariſe to that knowledge, and faith, and diligence that is in you, let not this grace be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>8 Though it be the commandement of God that you ſhould giue, yet that this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may come more willingly from you, I haue thought it good therefore rather to
<pb facs="tcp:20972:5"/> allure you thereunto by the examples of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>9 If a man ſhal thinke that the poore are not ſuch worthy men, that for their ſake a man ſhould diminiſh that which he hath: howe much more then might Chriſt our Lord haue ſo thought.</p>
               <p>10 If you ſhall performe this duty, you ſhall haue this comfort, that it was a thinge done by aduiſe and counſell: and therefore you may be bold to venture vpon it, being ſuch a duty as you your ſelues alſo are alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perſwaded that it ought to be done.</p>
               <p>11 I would haue you to conſider, that when you haue purpoſed to do this thing, yet it is not therfore done except you ſtirre vp your ſelues anew to the doing of it.</p>
               <p>12 As for the charges of houſe-keeping or any ſuch matter, neuer obiect it, for god only requires that we ſhould giue of that which we haue.</p>
               <p>13 The Lord his meaning is, not that we ſhould giue vnto thoſe that haue leſſe neede then our ſelues.</p>
               <p>14 But that they in like manner, ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20972:5"/> giue vnto you, when you haue neede to be releeued by them.</p>
               <p>15 That there might be equality, and all indifferency vſed that may be.</p>
               <p>16 You may ſee that god his meaning is, that you ſhoud giue, in that he hath ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp ſuch an excellent man, to mooue you to this duty.</p>
               <p>17 For he was quickly mooued euen of his owne accord, to performe that duty, that is wont to be accounted ſo thankeles: whereby you may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what a good forwardneſſe he hoped for at your hands.</p>
               <p>18 It ſhould be a meanes to make you giue more liberally, becauſe you ſee that the collectours are excellent men, and will moſt certenly deliuer that which you ſhall giue.</p>
               <p>19 For how much you doe detract fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuing: ſo much doe you detract from the glory of god, that is, to be magnified in the fidellity of thoſe men: and ſo much the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of alſo are you, from ſhewing a ready minde, hauing ſuch incouragements to go by. For by the greatnes of thoſe that goe
<pb facs="tcp:20972:6"/> vpon this embaſſage, you may well thinke that the matter is great that is to be delt in.</p>
               <p>20 21 The manner alſo of the dealing of theſe men, in the deliuery of that they are put in truſt with all: is ſuch as none may doubt of their fidellitie in this buſines.</p>
               <p>22 The diligence alſo that they will vſe, beeing incouraged therevnto, by the good hope that they conceiue of you, ſhould not a little mooue you.</p>
               <p>23 In that Titus was ſuch a one, as the Apoſtle thought to be a meete man to be his companion, and fellow helper, in that great worke of the miniſterie. And that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards themſelues, which had ſo good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of him: no man therfore needeth to doubt of his fidellitie in this buſines. As for the other two brethren, they were the meſſengers, not of particular men, but of the whole churches.</p>
               <p>24 He doth therefore infer vpon his former ſpeech, that that which was done before them, was done before al the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whoſe meſſengers they were: who are euen the glory of Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:6"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Corinth. chap.</hi> 9.</bibl>
               <p>If there were not ſome other ſpeciall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, it were ſuperfluous for me to write vnto you touching miniſtering to the ſaints.</p>
               <p>2 For the redines of your minde this way is ſuch, that I boaſt my ſelfe of your preparation, (&amp; that ſo long agoe) to thoſe of Macedonia, &amp; this your zeale hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked many.</p>
               <p>3 4 But yet leſt thoſe, to whome I haue ſo much boaſted of you, ſhould at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (to your and my further ſhame) finde you vnprepared: to prevent this great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, I haue ſent the brethren to giue you knowledge of this thing before they come.</p>
               <p>5 That you may finiſh your benevole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leſt it being to be finiſhed at their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, they ſhould account you a ſparing and not a forward people.</p>
               <p>6 Remember therefore that your bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, is as ſeed which is not loſt when it is throwne into the ground; but the leſſe you ſow, the leſſe crop ſhall you haue: and
<pb facs="tcp:20972:7"/> the more you ſowe, the more plentiful wil your harueſt be.</p>
               <p>7 Alwaies provided, that the manner of your ſowing be with purpoſe of heart, and not onely to avoide the hard opinion that thoſe of Macedonia might otherwiſe haue of you, for God requires of you that it ſhould be your owne wil &amp; your owne deede.</p>
               <p>8 Neither be you afraid if you be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, that then you ſhall never hold out in this duty, for God that hath giuen you a promiſe, is able alſo to performe it.</p>
               <p>9 For there is a generall proclamation of this mercy, to all that will performe this duty.</p>
               <p>10 And we haue a pledge of this his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, in that he bleſſeth the ſowing of the husbandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo that thereby he hath wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to maintaine his family, and alſo to ſowe againe (and that more plentifully) the next yeere after, he that doth the one will alſo performe the other.</p>
               <p>11 That thereby you might be made rich in the beſt thing, euen in the liberality
<pb facs="tcp:20972:7"/> which being practiſed towardes a people, that by the preaching of the Goſpell haue learned whome to thanke for it, god alſo by this meanes may haue that honour that is due vnto him.</p>
               <p>12 For this ſacrifice (as I may tearme it) is not onely not a waſting in vaine of the things that we haue, beeing beſtowed where neede is, and fitting the neceſsities of thoſe that are euen our owne fleſh; but God alſo thereby hath that duty perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him, euen the duty of thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that of all duties he doth moſt highly account of: and that not alſo by a fewe but by many.</p>
               <p>13 Howſoeuer god accepteth very well of thankes for euery of his common mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, yet when his great gift of humbling any vnto the Goſpel is acknowledged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the world doth not make any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckoning of it: this thankefulnes is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God in the higheſt degre. Seeing therefore that thankes this waies ſhall be giuen vnto God by meanes of our bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe, which beeing giuen in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:20972:8"/> is a token of the ſubmitting of you ſelues therevnto. If any thing, then this thing ſhould incourage you vnto this duty. Beſides this God ſhall alſo haue thanke for the good that redoundes thereby euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bodies of men.</p>
               <p>14 In reſpect of your ſelues, alſo your releife ſhal be to great purpoſe, for the lord hath put a bleſsing into the handes of af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flicted perſons, to beſtow vpon thoſe that doe releeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thoſe that of all men ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do moſt with God ſhal pray for you. Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſides this to haue good men long to be in our company, to delight to heate of vs, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a greater bleſsing then we take it to be, which notwithſtanding ſhal come to paſſe by meanes of this duty.</p>
               <p>15 I am not able to expreſſe the excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lency of the great gift of God, when he o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peneth mens hearts to releeue their poore brethren: and I nothing doubt, but that God will worke this great thing in you. And therefore thankes be vnto God ſo this vſpeakable gift.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biblical_commentary">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20972:8"/>
            <head>THE LECTVRES OF SAMVEL BIRD VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 8. and 9. chapters of the ſecond epiſtle to the Corinthians.</head>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>We doe you alſo to wit brethren, of the grace of God beſtowed vpon the Churches of Maceaonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Becauſe in great triall of affliction their ioy abounded, and their moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame pouertie abounded vnto their rich liberalitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>For to their power I beare record, yea and beyond their power they vvere vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>And praied vs vvith great inſtance that we would receiue the grace &amp; fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the miniſtring which is towards the Saints.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:20972:9"/>
            <p>1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſcarſitie of all things ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene ſo long time vpon our lande, as our fathers neuer knew the like, it muſt needes be a very neceſſarie doctrine that ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard vs helpe and comfort againſt it: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if we conſider how acceptable a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice the relieuing of our brethren will be at that time when we would moſt gladly be comforted. For though the Lord in mercie will reward euery good worke of his ſeruants, yet by a certaine kinde of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie the relieuing of the poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt Ieſus is in a moſt ſpeciall manner remembred, Matth. 25. Becauſe therefore the holy Ghoſt hath ſet downe his will vnto vs more fully and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touching this dutie then in any one place of the whole Bible throughout: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing purpoſed through the aſsiſtance of God his grace to ſpeake of the doctrine of reliefe, I thought it good to make choiſe of this portion of ſcripture. In theſe two chapters the Apoſtle goeth forwarde to take vp the handling of thoſe things that
<pb facs="tcp:20972:9"/> he had mentioned in his firſt epiſtle &amp; the laſt chapter, the beginning of the chapter: &amp; this was the occaſion of his ſpeech. The prophet Agabus tould of a famine that ſhould be throughout all the world, by meanes whereof the poore churches of Ieruſalem were in great danger of periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they were not greatly releeued: wherevpon the Apoſtle tooke order that the Gentiles might be mooued to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute vnto them. Act. 11. 28. Gal. 2. 10. The Apoſtle therefore hauing mooued the Corinthians in this matter, 1. Cor. 16. 1. and finding them not ſo forward as was to be wiſhed, he prouokes them againe vnto this duty, with a large exhortation, &amp; with many arguments. 1 And becauſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples are of great force to drawe men vnto du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he therefore certifieth them what the poore churches of Macedonia had done in this matter; by the which practiſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, we are taught this leſſon: namely, that when we vnderſtand of any, that haue dealt liberally and bountifully with their poore brethren in theſe hard times, that
<pb facs="tcp:20972:10"/> we ſhould be talking to them of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for it is a forcible motiue to mooue them to this dutie. When the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of giuing is onely ſtood vpon, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is woont to be made, that we ſhould doe ſo. But who doth it? when therefore we bring forth the parties that haue done ſo, that ſhift is taken away. The argument that the Apoſtle doth here vſe is of very great force, in ſo much that when no other argument will preuaile, this is thought meete euen then to perſwade, Rom. 11. 14. when the Iewes had reiected the Goſpell. The Apoſtle thought that the telling of them that the Gentiles had receiued it, would be of force to recouer them againe. And to ſpeak more particularly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this preſent dutie; Salomon when he will mooue euen the hard hearted vſurer to leaue off his hard dealing, and to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the poore, he vſeth no other reaſon but this that the Apoſtle hath here, Prov. 28. 8. namely to prouoke him by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of others: <hi>He,</hi> ſaith Salomon, <hi>that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth his riches by vſurie and intereſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20972:10"/> gathereth them for him that will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to the poore.</hi> The vſurer hath no ſuch meaning that his goods ſhould be ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, but Salomon tells him that it will fall out ſo. And it were better that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould beſtowe his goods well, then that others ſhould doe it when it ſhall be no thanke to him. If it ſhould mooue the vſurer when he is tolde what will fall out hereafter, when men therefore be tolde what hath beene done alreadie, it ſhould much more affect them. Men commonly are wont to certifie their neighbours of the eſtate of thoſe that purchaſe and grow in wealth: but this is a meanes to worke enuie in them, and to mooue them to the like worldlines. The certificate that is here ſpoken of, is a thouſand times better: for it raiſeth vp the affections of men to the loue of mercie. We are alſo further to note out of the firſt verſe, that the Apoſtle doth account it a benefite to the giuer that he doth giue. For the Saints of Ieruſalem were the men that were relieued, yet the Apoſtle ſaith, I certifie you of the grace or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20972:11"/> gift of God beſtowed vpon the churches of Macedonia that were the giuers. And this is agreeable to that ſaying of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, <hi>It is an happier thing to giue then to receiue,</hi> Act. 20. 35. And Paul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this matter, Philip. 4. 17. when he telleth them that he was deſirous to haue them bountifull, not ſaith he, that I deſire a gift: but I deſire the fruit that may further your reckning. The ſpech that the Apoſtle doth vſe is borrowed from the practiſe of ſuch as vſe traffique one with an other in this world. As he that vttereth wares to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chappeman, the more he vttereth the greater will his gaine be in the account when he comes to reckon: ſo is it in this matter. Men commonly account it a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, a loſſe and an hindrance, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth it a grace and a gift, that poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould giue as they did. If men had had the inditing of this ſtorie, they would one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue told vs what a great gift the Saints of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiued of the Macedonians: but to haue written thus, I doe you to wit concerning the grace of God beſtowed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20972:11"/> vpon the Churches of the Macedonians: it would neuer haue come into their heade but we are taught to acquaint our mouths with ſuch ſpeaches. Beſides other reaſons if it be conſidered that in the fearefull fall of many, it is vſed as an argument to aſſure men that they are not of that number when they are bountifull to the Saints of God, Hebr. 6. 9. and 10. we ſhall then ſee that not without cauſe it is called a grace or a gift. 2 He doth nowe tell vs what that grace was that was beſtowed vpon them, namely that though they were in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, yet were they not oppreſſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but had faith in the Lord, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in him with ioy of others, opened their hearts to giue plentifully of that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which they had vnto their brethren. By reioycing in God, they prouided very well for themſelues in their affliction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt worldy ſorrow; for as in the bodie, cold diſeaſes are healed by hot things: ſo in the ſoule, worldly griefe is healed by godly ioy. If men in their troubles would reioice in the Lord, they would not then thinke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20972:12"/> other things, health, wealth, liberty, or any other worldly commodity ſo delightfull: that for the want thereof they would fret againſt God. And if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will examine whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ouertaken of fretting, they ſhall finde that at that time they did not reioice in the Lord, that they did not delight in his word, muſing much vpon his faithful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, vntil they were delighted therwith. A man cannot be alwaies in griefe, and we would gladly delight in ſomething: if not in God, then in worldly matters, which when we ſee that we haue not, then we fret; and here we ſee a difference betweene ſpirituall and fleſhly ioy. The one, if any thing falls out otherwiſe then well, the life of it is cleane take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away: the other though it be hindred with troubles yet it ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth. The ioy that he ſpeakes of was in the Lord, which alwaies remaineth good and gratious vnto his ſeruants, to miniſter matter of reioycing vnto them. Phillip. 4. 4. The reioycing in trouble, and their bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe are both ioyned together, &amp; are made one and the ſame grace: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20972:12"/> heart is bent to beſtowe any thing, there is ioy, the heart is opened and inlarged. On the other ſide, when the heart is oppreſſed with griefe, it is ſo pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vp that it is nothing ready to any duty. Hebr. 12. 12. <hi>Lift vp your weake handes &amp; your weake knees</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. The wicked by buiſiyng them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about other matters, labour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the ſence of euil, with ſporting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and by driuing away phanſies as they ſay: but the godly euen from the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction gather matter of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort; <hi>The Lord will doe me good eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for this mans railing,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, 2. Sam. 16. They co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with this, that whome the Lord doth loue, he doth chaſtice. When men are in trouble, they thinke that they are to be borne withall though they minde no mans matters but their owne: but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe you looke ſo ſad, ſaith Ioſeph, to thoſe that were in priſon, Gen. 40. 7. And Paul a priſoner writeth comfortably for Oneſimus. And the Macedonians in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions comforted and relieued the poore Saints of Ieruſalem. 3 By ſaying that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20972:13"/> they gaue aboue their ſtrength, his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, not that they gaue ſo that they were forced to take of others, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the 12. verſe: for that were to rob Peter and to pay Paul. But this his meaning is, that beſides giuing as much as they were able: they wiſhed alſo that they could giue more; for as in ſtrait hearted men, their wil is not ſo large as their gift, though it be but a little that they doe giue. So in open hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted men, though they giue as much as they are able, yet is their deſire to doe good, larger then the gift: they are ſo mindeful to pleaſure the party whome they loue, that they forget themſelues, 1. Cor. 13. 5. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth offer himſelfe to be a witneſſe to teſtify in this matter. He no doubt, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired of their eſtate, that he might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to teſtifie: otherwiſe the Corinthes might haue obiected, that euery man, euen thoſe that haue mony enough, when any good bargaine is offered; yet when there is any ſpeech of giuing, they will then be accounted poore men. The Apoſtle ſaith, that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtify that it was not ſo with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20972:13"/> Macedonians. And we are to obſerue, that although other Churches did contribute as well as thoſe of Macedonia, as namely the Galatians, 1. Cor. 16. 1. and the Romans, Rom. 1. 5. 26. yet becauſe thoſe of Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia (though poore) were forwarder then the reſt, therefore doth he make choice of propounding their example both to the Corinths, and alſo to the Romanes: for the Lord looketh not to the greatnes of the gift, but to the greatnes of the affection, which cannot be great in a rich man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he giueth very much. And therefore the Apoſtle doth not ſpeake of the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of money which they gaue, but he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth vnto them their giuing aboue their ſtrength, that thereby he might raiſe vp the like bountifull affections among the Corinthians. 4 Their readines in giuing is further commended: for they did not ſtay vntill they were intreated, but they offer and that earneſtly their liberalitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were intreated. The common manner is to thinke that men haue neede when they begge, or ſome others make
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20972:14"/> requeſt in their behalfe, but theſe men ſaw that the Church of Ieruſalem could not chooſe but want, without any admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This forcing of men to goe a begging is a very diſorderly courſe: for thoſe that haue leaſt neede will be forwardeſt in beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: and therefore <hi>he that will not labour let him not eate,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. On the other ſide, many will be in very great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie before they will begge. This for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of men to aske is a ſhaming of them, nay it is a ſhaming of a man when another beggeth for him in his preſence. For if a man be aſhamed when a man muſt bring forth his owne meate, beeing but a poore diet, and eate it in the preſence of thoſe that haue a more liberall diet before them, 1. Cor. 11. 22. then is it a ſhame to begge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens meate. The relieuing of wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes is called an honouring of them, 1. Tim. 5. when we account them worthie to be relieued: but ſhaming and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them cannot ſtand together. That reliefe is moſt acceptable vnto God, that is moſt comfortable to the parties that be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20972:14"/> but giuing without begging is moſt comfortable: therefore that muſt needs be moſt acceptable. A man his friend may doe many things for another which himſelfe may not ſo well doe, amongſt which things this that is here ſpoken of, is one of them. In that the Macedonians did offer ſo earneſtly before the Apoſtle would take it, it may appeare that though the Apoſtle would faine haue the poore relieued, yet he was warie &amp; circumſpect of whome he did take it; ſo that all that is offered, muſt not be taken neither for our ſelues nor for others, but conſideration muſt be had what is conuenient. When Abſolon bad Dauid to a feaſt he refuſed to goe, 2. Sam. 13. 25. for feare of beeing ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeable: for when inferiours inuite their ſuperiours in a brauerie, they are wont to be aboue meaſure in their proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Dauid therefore would giue no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to any ſuch courſe. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe except there be ſome ſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there is want of loue in it. And therefore the Apoſtle doth make an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20972:15"/> in his owne defence, when he refuſeth the kindneſſe of the Corinthes, 2. Cor. 11. 11. The cauſe wherefore he doth not receiue the liberality of the Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, before it was forced vpon him with great intreaty was, becauſe of their poore eſtate. Other cauſes alſo there may be of this refuſall, as namely when a man ſeeth that the party that offers the gift, his other behauiour is not anſwerable and ſutable to this pretented kindnes: but that he ſeeketh thereby to inſult vpon his brother, and to giue him to vnderſtand thereby, that he is able to beſtowe ſomewhat vpon him. When a man by receiuing a gift, ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge himſelfe of that liberty that it is meete a man ſhould haue in his dealings &amp; conuerſation with him, then a man is to giue no allowance to any ſuch matter, as may appeare by the example of Abraham, Gen. 14. 23. For it is al one as if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſell his birth right for a meſſe of pottage. It falls out ſometimes that when a man is to deale with a chapman, he will bidde him to dinner, but he will make him pay deere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20972:15"/> for it in the bargaine. He doth againe call the gift of the Macedonians a grace, thereby to drawe men the rather to giue. For that which makes men ſo loth to giue is, becauſe they thinke that it is their own, not conſidering that they are onely diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the manifold graces of god, 1. Pet. 4. 10. as ſtewards, and muſt be countable to their maſter for them, whether they haue vſed them to the beſt advantage of their maſters credit. Luke, 16. 1. The name of grace will alſo take away the opinion of deſert; Rom. 11. 6. And therefore Dauid when he had made ſuch goodly prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the moſt glorious temple that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was in the world. 1. Chro. 29. 14. yet ſaith he, we haue giuen thee that which is thine owne. He calleth it the fellowſhip of the miniſtring, becauſe the Apoſtle did go with the releefe that was gathered, 1. Cor. 16. 4. For then will men be willing, when they knowe that the party that doth carrie it, will diſtribute it faithfully. On the other ſide, we ſee howe vnwilling men be to giue to proctours, of whoſe truſt &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20972:16"/> they may very well doubt: and that the poore houſes for whome they gather ſhall haue but a litle of the collection. If therefore we will haue men willing to giue, we muſt be very carefull to appoint ſuch collectours as are of great credit with the conſciences of ſuch as are to giue. It is not alſo to be omitted, that the poore here and throughout theſe two chapters, are tearmed by the name of Saints, which is an honourable title: and therefore when he will put the Corinths in minde of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of their eſtate, he telleth them that they are Saints by calling, 1. Cor. 1. 2. by ſanctification is the image of God renued within vs. The Saints of God be thoſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whome all our delight ſhould be ſet, Pſal. 16. 3. to mooue therefore our ſelues and others to giue to the poore, we are to conſider that they are the Saints of God. The thing that makes vs deſpiſe them and be careles of them, is the forgetting that they are rich in faith, and heires apparant to the kingdome of heauen, Iam. 5. 2. The Apoſtle was not ignorant that diuerſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20972:16"/> of thoſe whome he ſpeaketh of were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnruly, and a man may thinke it a ſtrange thing, that the Apoſtle needed to be praied for in this matter; for who would doubt that comming with releefe, of his beeing welcome vnto them, yet we ſee he prayeth the Romans, cap. 15. 31. to pray for him that this his ſeruice might be accepted of the Saints, Act. 6. 1. If men be mooued to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to poore ſchollers in the vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, from whence the Goſpell hath ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into all parts of the kingdome, anſwer is wont to be made, that they are ſo proud in their apparell, that it is pittie that they ſhould haue any releefe: nowe though ſome forget themſelues that waies, yet all doe not, and they make choiſe of the beſt. If men would accuſtome themſelues to account them the poore ſaints of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, as the Apoſtle doth call the poore people of Ieruſalem by that name; and that alſo when he doth thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Rom. 15. 31. then would men be more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to giue. The like may be ſaid of the poore people of God euery where. VVe
<pb facs="tcp:20972:17"/> account as well of other things, when they be in the handes of the poore, as we doe when they be in the handes of the rich. In a market or faire, if a poore man will buy any thing, his money ſhall be as well eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of as the money of the rich: and if he will giue but a penny more for a thing, he ſhall haue it before another: his coyne is as good ſiluer as an other mans. And why ſhould not ſanctification be eſteemed of as well in the poorer ſort as in other men? The Apoſtle calleth them Saints which doe now liue, and needed releefe, which is good alſo to obſerue. For if a man ſhould be of the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the papiſts in this point namely, to account no man a Saint whilſt he liueth, what great heart ſhould a man haue to releeue any. On the other ſide, to conſider that in the ſcripture the ſeruantes of God are not called Saints after their death, but onely whileſt they be aliue: and after their death they haue other names giuen them, as Kemniſius againſt the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Trent, doth very well obſerue, may be a meanes to pull men from Idollatry.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20972:17"/> True it is, that corruption is mingled with holineſſe, as water is mingled with wine; yet we call it wine and not water: ſo muſt we account the other Saints, though they haue wants in them. The meaning of the Apoſtle, is not that onely the ſaints of God ſhould be releeued: for if thine enemy hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, feede him. But howſoeuer we muſt do good vnto all, yet eſpecially to the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould of faith, Gal. 6. they muſt haue the priueledge of an elder brother, euen a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion. If the almes of ſome fewe of the Papiſts which are forwarder in giuing then their fellows, were examined by this rule, it would not dazle the eyes of ſome men as it doth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>5 <hi>And this they did not as we looked for: but gaue their own ſelues, firſt to the Lord, and after vnto vs by the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6 <hi>That we ſhould exhort Titus, that as he had begun, ſo he would accompliſh the ſame grace among you alſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>They are commended for beeing boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful beyond the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtle. The profeſsion of the Goſpell doth as it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20972:18"/> were, promis the releeuing of their poore brethren, ſo that all that here of the one, will hope of the other: ſo that thoſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers which doe not performe this duty, are called in the ſcripture cloudes without raine. And it is dangerous in the higheſt degree to diſapoint me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hope which they conceiue of them; for they are ſubiect to the curſe which was denounced by Chriſt againſt the figge tree, <hi>neuer fruite growe on thee hereafter.</hi> But theſe people are here commended for performing more then euer the Apoſtle did looke for. And we knowe he looked that euen a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring man ſhould giue to him which hath more neede then himſelfe, Eph. 4. The cauſe of their liberality is ſaid to be this, namely that they gaue ouer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto the Lord, they rezined their wil to the will of God: when a man denyeth himſelfe, he will ſoone be brought to giue where neede is, and good reaſon it is that we ſhould doe ſo, for we are not our own 1. Cor. 6. We muſt not liue to our ſelues but to the Lord, referring al to his honour,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20972:18"/> Rom. 12. 1. here I am to doe thy will, O Lord. VVhen men were once ſubdued by the Goſpel, they laide their money downe at the Apoſtles feete, Act. 4. 35. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſaide, they <hi>gaue themſelues first vnto the Lord, and after to vs by the will of God. Shall I,</hi> ſaith Dauid, <hi>giue vnto God that that coſteth me nothing,</hi> 2. Sam. 24. 24. 6 They are ſaid to haue done good, not onely by their example, but alſo by their ſpeach. For they intreated the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to deale with Titus to goe forwarde with that which he had begunne. By this ſpeach we may firſt of all obſerue the great modeſtie that was in the Apoſtle, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired not to be accounted the onely man that dealt with the matter of reliefe: but did moſt willingly acknowledge the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of other men in this matter. VVhen therefore we vnderſtand that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue dealt a long time together in inflaming the mindes of men to a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full regarde of their poore brethren, it is meete that it ſhould be thought vpon. The mindes of men are like to a fire of greene
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20972:19"/> wood; if in ſuch a fire a man beſtoweth much blowing and puffing, it may be that at the laſt a litle blaſt ſetteth all on a flame: yet will no wiſe man attribute the flaming of that wood to that litle blaſt, but to the long puffing that went before: ſo is it in this matter. Therefore our Sauiour Chriſt when he will teach his diſciples to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and modeſt, <hi>Other men,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>haue laboured</hi> (meaning the prophets which were before them) <hi>and you haue entrea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their labours,</hi> Ioh. 4. 38. It was of great force to mooue the Corinthians to libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, when they were told that the church of the Macedonians did looke to haue it ſo: for men are loath but that other chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhould haue a good opinion of them. Beſides this, though Titus was very readie to performe this dutie, yet becauſe he was loath to ouercharge any, it was to be thought that he would be more ſparing in his ſpeaches this waies: but when he was incouraged thereunto by other, and thoſe alſo poorer Churches, this no doubt did greatly embolden him vnto this dutie.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20972:19"/> By this meanes alſo the Corinthians could take the leſſe exception againſt his ſpeach. For if Titus alone of his owne accord one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had made this motion, anſwer might haue bin made, that Titus had no experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence this waies, namely how many waies charges goe out with them that haue dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the world. But when other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which know what theſe charges doe meane, doe yet account it needeful to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, this ſtoppeth the mouthes of ſuch as would gaineſay this exhortation. Theſe men did not onely giue, but they did alſo procure other men to giue. If they had onely giuen, though this had beene much in reſpect of their pouertie, yet otherwiſe the parties to whome they gaue, ſhould haue receiued but a little. But when beſides their owne gift, they mooue others to giue, this amounteth to a great deale. To mooue others to giue is highly accounted of, 2. King. 4. 8. for becauſe of this dutie is the Sunamite ſo highly accounted of. And as in warre, drummers are neceſſarie to make others fight: but then are they moſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20972:20"/> neceſſarie when they alſo themſelues will fight: then are ſuch as ſtirre vp others to giue moſt neceſſarie. If men in a towne or pariſh haue any ſparkle of zeale in them, ſuch drummers will make them giue. And if men can not ſtirre vp others to giue immediately by themſelues for want of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, yet ſhould they be ſo zealous as to ſtirre vp by others, as the Macedonians mooued Titus by Paul. It is no reproch but an honourable ſeruice, to begge for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. For this that is here ſaide of the Macedonians, is not ſpoken to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, but to their commendation. They were not of their mindes that except they be the firſt moouers, they will do nothing. A couetous heart is glad to take occaſion to keepe himſelfe from dutie by ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes. Theſe men that be ſo affected, may well be compared to reſtie horſes, that wil neither goe of their owne accord without the ſpurre, and yet if they be ſpurred, then they will goe backward. The baddeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants thinke moſt ſcorne to be quickned vp vnto dutie: but an humble minded man
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20972:20"/> or woman will ſoone acknowledge that they ſtand in neede of admonition: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we muſt take away preaching and all admonition. The manner alſo of moouing Paul to deale with Titus is not to be omitted: for they acknowledge the forwardnes of Titus in that he had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die begunne; ſo that they doe not ſtir him vp in a bragging manner, as if vnder the pretenſe of moouing of him their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was to vaunt themſelues aboue him: for ſuch a kinde of dealing would haue hindered the perſwaſion. Beſides this it ſhould alſo haue beene daungerous to their owne ſoules: they onely as it were put him in minde of that which he had begunne to doe before in other churches.</p>
            <q>
               <p>7 <hi>Therfore as ye aboundin euery thing, in faith and word, and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your loue towards vs: ſo euen ſee that you abound in this grate alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8 <hi>This I ſay not by commandement: but becauſe of the diligence of others, therefore proue I the naturalnes of your loue.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20972:21"/>
            <p>As before he doth exhort them from the liberality of other Churches, ſo doth he nowe perſwade them by their owne forwardnes in other things: that as they had faith, and had knowledge, and vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to impart this their faith vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and were alſo not idle, but diligent in their affaires and alſo loued the Apoſtle of whome they learned theſe things: ſo he would haue them alſo abound in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing vnto other their poore brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When a man heareth or ſeeth others which are plentiful in giuing, yet they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake of matters of religion in ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull a manner as we can. We are then in great danger to ſet ſo light by this grace of God in them For we thinke they want that knowledge which we haue, but the Apoſtle teacheth vs a contrary leſſon, namely that to thoſe graces which he had commended in them, they ſhould adde this grace of giuing alſo, 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 5. When a man heateth of any man of account, that can ſpeake of matters of religion, more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plentifully then any of their profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20972:21"/> and calling throughout the whole countrey, that he is a graue and a learned man, and of great iudgement in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures yet he ſhall be noted in liberality to be nothing ſutable to that portion which God hath giuen him, not nothing anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the frankeneſſe of other men, which haue neither that wealth nor kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge which he hath: this is a great ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh vnto him. And it makes men ſet leſſe by thoſe excellent gifts of knowledge and ſpeech a great deale, then otherwiſe they would doe. No doubt but that theſe men amongeſt the Corinthians which were thus rich in knowledg, gaue ſomething to good vſes: or els the Apoſtle would neuer haue vouchſafed to haue made any honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable mention of their other gifts. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were more ſcant in giuing, then men of meaner vnderſtanding, the Apoſtle would haue them to abound in this duty alſo, which would giue as great a grace vnto them in the eyes of God and man, as any knowledge, or ſpeech, or any, or all the gifts they had, putting them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20972:22"/> for that that is to be deſired of a man, is his goodnes. Thoſe that haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſpeach in great aboundance, are woont to be noted as chiefe men among the profeſſours: when men therefore ſhall note them to be ſomwhat skant in giuing, they will eaſily imagine that all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours are farre more skant, as in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo in giuing: thus doe men bring diſgrace to the whole church of God. And it grieues a man when he heareth a man of knowledge noted for hardnes, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he would be partiall, cannot tell what to ſay in his behalfe. 8 The Apoſtle would haue this dutie of giuing to come naturally from them, as it were of their owne accord: and therefore he ſaith, <hi>I ſay not this by commaundement.</hi> He might no doubt haue commaunded them as they would anſwer to the contrarie at their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt perill, when Chriſt ſhall come to iudgement, 1. Tim. 6. 17. but for loues ſake he chuſeth to deale otherwiſe, that this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might not be of neceſsitie, but willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Philemon 14. <hi>Generoſus animus,</hi> as one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20972:22"/> ſaith, <hi>facilius ſequitur quàm trahitur:</hi> therefore the Apoſtle doth labour ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to allure them by the example of other churches.</p>
            <q>
               <p>9 <hi>For ye know the grace of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that he beeing rich for your ſakes became poore, that ye through his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie might be made rich.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>To ſtrengthen the example of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians, he doth warrant it as good by his example that is to order all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world. The Apoſtles, as it may appeare by their writing, in all duties did much looke vpon the patterne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, euen as painters looke much vpon the partie whome they meane to paint out. When they would not haue vs ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our reputation, they alleadge the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt, Philip. 2. 7. When they will mooue ſeruants quietly to put vp the wrongs and iniuries of their maſters, they bring forth the example of Chriſt, 1. Pet. 2. 21. When they will mooue husbands to loue their wiues, they alleadge the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt. VVhen they would haue vs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20972:23"/> not loue in word but in deede, and to lay downe our liues for our brethren, if neede be, they propound vnto vs the example of Chriſt, Ioh. 3. VVhen they will haue vs to beginne to loue our brethren, and not to tarrie vntill they beginne to loue vs, they propound vnto vs the example of Chriſt: So here moouing vs to liberalitie, he doth ſet before our eyes the example of Chriſt, who beeing the heyre of the world, Hebr. 1. yet to make vs rich, was content not to haue an houſe to put his head in. If we thinke that the poore are not ſuch worthy men, that for their ſakes a man ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh that which he hath, then much more might Chriſt thinke ſo. As therfore the Apoſtle ſaith in another place, <hi>Conſider him,</hi> that is to ſay the greatnes of him, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. 12. <hi>that indured ſuch ſpeaking againſt of ſinners:</hi> ſo is it ſaide here, that euen our Lord beeing rich, for our ſakes became poore: and therefore when men will not giue of their ſuperfluitie, they are farre from following the example of Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>10 <hi>And I ſhew my minde herein: for this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20972:23"/> is expedient for you which haue begun not to doe onely, but alſo to will a yeare agoe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>11 <hi>Now therefore performe to doe it al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo, that as there was a readines to will, euen ſo you may performe it of that vvhich you haue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>12 <hi>For if there be firſt a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>In that the Apoſtle doth offer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto their conſideration, aduiſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſaying, <hi>I ſhew you my minde herein,</hi> we muſt not thinke but that this aduiſe of his is to haue the force and authoritie of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. VVhen the prophet Dauid ſaith, that <hi>the word of God is his counſeller,</hi> pſal. 119. 24. his meaning is not but that it ſhould command him. But onely his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is to allure them ſweetely, and not to drawe them by commaundement to the duty of giuing. He ſpeakes as a meane man may ſpeake to any ſupericur, for the counſell we knowe may aduiſe the prince, though otherwiſe ſhee be to command them: and when ſhee doth follow their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20972:24"/> ſhee is not drawne againſt her will: but ſweetly allured by that equity, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which ſhe ſeeth to be in their ſpeeches. In this manner doth the Apoſtle perſwade them to this duty in this place: ſo that though he doth aduiſe them, yet muſt we knowe that this his aduiſe, is to haue the place of a commandement. We muſt not gather as the Papiſts doe from ſuch ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that their be in the ſcripture, counſels and commaundements: the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we muſt of neceſsity doe, but for counſels, we are at liberty whether we wil do them or no. And therfore thoſe which follow the counſell and aduiſe that is ſet down in the ſcripture, becauſe they doe more then the lawe requireth, doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore works of ſupererogation, as thoſe do that liue a ſingle life, that loue their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and doe ſuch like things. This is no ſuch aduiſe as men may chooſe whether they will doe it or no: na, this and ſuch like ſpeeches doth magnify the word of God in that it is called our counſell, and in that the interpreters thereof, are called our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelloures:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20972:24"/> for thereby we haue the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of kings and princes. Who when any matter is brought vnto them, are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſend to their ſecretary to call their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell together. So when we haue any thing to doe, we muſt call for our counſellers the Prophets and Apoſtles, and ſuch as can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret their writings vnto vs: for they are the counſellers of the worlde. <hi>In all thy waies,</hi> ſaith Salomon, <hi>acknowledge the Lord and he ſhall direct thee in his waies.</hi> And in theſe hard times, if men would knowe what regard they ſhould haue of their poore brethren, they ſhould conſult with theſe two chapters, wherein the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt of purpoſe hath ſet down his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will and pleaſure vnto vs. The worlde thinkes, that the miniſters of the Goſpell, take too much vpon them, when they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe men in theſe matters: as if men were not wiſe inough to beſtowe that they meane to giue, but that the miniſters muſt aduiſe them. But there is more wiſdome required in this thing then the world is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of: we knowe what became of him
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20972:25"/> which refuſed to follow the counſell of the auncient, 1. King. 12. So when men ſhall chooſe rather to followe the counſell of wild young men, that would haue a man ſpend that he hath at drinkings which are needleſſe, then vpon their poore brethren; we know what they may looke for, with that rich man in the 6. of Luke. To mooue them the rather to follow his aduiſe, he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them that it is expedient or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for he that is wiſe is wiſe for himſelfe as Salomon ſaith, Prouerbes 9. This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is drawn from profit, is woont to be in ſteede of a 1000. arguments: for tell a man thus, you are not your owne friend if you take not this courſe, you haue ſaid inough: if he be perſwaded of the truth of this ſaying, it ſhall be in ſteed of a thouſand ſayings. VVhen Parents would haue their children to worke, they will let them haue their owne earnings, they knowe that if any thing will drawe them to worke, that will doe it. Howe it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient or profitable, we may ſee in the 9. chapter and eight verſe, he tells them that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20972:25"/> they were willing to this duty a yeere a goe, onely it was laid a ſide by reaſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, ſo that they were already per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the thing ought to be done: ſo that he needed not to ſpend his time in proouing that it ought to be done; for this was already agreed vpon. A man may giue for feare of lawe or for feare of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit, for what wil me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay if I ſhould giue nothing: In this manner a man will giue his purſe to a theife, but to doe this thing willingly is thankeworthy. This willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is neceſſary as in all duties, ſo in this: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe a man ſhall haue many pulbackes to keepe him from this duty; the children and kindred thinke that all is to little for them, and yet we read that Iob had ſeuen ſonnes and three daughters, Iob. 1. 2. yet did he not eate his murſels alone, but the fatherleſſe, did grow vp with him, he ſawe none to periſh for want of cloathing, the ſtranger did not lodge in the ſtreete; men that are of that place which Iob was of, thinke that by reaſon of that countinance that they are to bare, &amp; their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20972:26"/> whileſt they liue with them, and after their death, that little or nothing is to be giuen, eſpecially when they haue ſo many ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes as Iob had and 3. daughters: But Iob was willing to giue, and therefore was not pulled away by any ſuch temptation from this duty. 11. Though they had a minde to giue, yet were they ſlack in performing their purpoſe, for this makes men ſecure, when they haue once a minde to giue, they then neuer doe miſtruſt themſelues, they thinke then it muſt needes be done without any further indeauour. But we muſt ſtrike the yron whileſt it is hot, if we tarry whileſt it be cold, it muſt haue a new heating before we can worke vpon it: we muſt pray vnto God when he hath giuen vs the will, that he would alſo giue vs the deede. In reſpect of men, alſo there is cauſe why we ſhould doe things with expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the deferring of hope is the fainting of the ſoule, and we ſhould not weary the eyes of the widdowe. The reaſon why ſometimes it is dangerous to doe a thing ſuddenly, is becauſe we haue not thought
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20972:26"/> of it ſufficiently: but when a thing is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purpoſed there can be no danger in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the expedition that may be. 12. Men are wont to obiect the charges of their family, which makes them that they cannot giue much, and they are aſhamed to giue a little. The Apoſtle takes away all ſuch delaies, by telling them that a man muſt giue according to that he hath, and not according to that he hath not: and this may miniſter good comfort to a man, for when one giueth what he may, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing accounted of of the Lord becauſe it is ſo little: but the Apoſtle doth aſſure vs that if a man giue according to his abillitie, God accepteth of it; And as in ſtrength a poore man which vſeth that little ſtrength which he hath, is better accounted of both of God and man, then ſome idle luſty fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe which hath foure times his ſtrength, and doth not vſe it. So he that hath but a little wealth, and yet doth well imploy that little which he hath, is a great deale more to be accounted of then thoſe idle wealthy men, that wil not put forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20972:27"/> Men in this matter muſt conſider that they haue to deale with God, from whome they can hide nothing: and therefore if they ſay that they giue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which they haue, beeing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding priuie to themſelues that they haue a great deale more then that which is ſutable to that which they giue, men may then deceiue themſelues: but as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God is not mocked,</hi> Galat. 6. 7.</p>
            <q>
               <p>13 <hi>Neither is it that other men ſhould be eaſed, and you grieued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>14 <hi>But vpon like condition at this time your aboundance ſupplieth their lacke, that alſo their aboundance may be for your lack, that there may be equalitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>15 <hi>As it is written, He that gathered much had nothing ouer, and he that gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red little had not the leſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>VVhen any is relieued the Apoſtle would not haue it to be with the burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of others. VVhen men be behinde hand, they are woont to get a licenſe to keepe an alehouſe, that thereby they may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20972:27"/> maintaine themſelues and their charge: for other poore men muſt come to their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to ſpend that which they haue, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the meane time what ſhall become of their wiues and children. This is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the rule of the Apoſtle, for when the poore oppreſſe the poore, it is like a raging raine that leaueth no foode. In ſome places poore men will beſtowe their money at marriages, when the parties that are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, are a great deale wealthier then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and their maſters, though they ſay other men ſhall be as bold with them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they marrie their children or ſeruants, yet there is no likelihood that poore men will euer be ſo bold with them. The Apoſtle hath no ſuch craft in his ſpeach. Not but that we muſt giue without looking for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch recompence. 14 Onely the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle aſſureth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that there is no partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in this thing. For if it ſhould pleaſe god to humble the Corinthswith like want, he would then be as earneſt with thoſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem to contribute vnto them. 15 He bringeth forth good proofe, that this mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20972:28"/> helpe ought to be amongſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, Exod. 16. 18. The people of Iſrael were fedde with Manna for a time, that thereby they might vnderſtande in their ordinarie foode for euer, euen when this Manna ſhould ceaſe, that they were not fedde by their owne labour or indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, but by the bleſsing of God, as we are taught, Deut. 8. 3. By this their Manna we may ſee as it were in a glaſſe, how to order our ſelues in our ordinarie foode. All the children of Iſrael were willed to gather Manna, and ſome of them gathered more according as they were more nimble or more ſtrong then others, and ſo they laide it all on an heape: howſoeuer ſome gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more then ſome other, yet none had more then an Homer full for his priuate vſe; by which meanes all had enough and none wanted. The Apoſtle would haue vs to make vſe of this matter: and although we haue no Homer to meaſure our goods withall, yet ſeeing neither we nor our children after vs, ſhould be intemperate in eating and drinking, in apparell, in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20972:28"/> in houſhold ſtuffe, or in any other matter, that ouerplus which wee haue ſhould be beſtowed vpon others. True it is that wee are to keepe poſſeſsion of that which God hath bleſſed vs withall, as a ſtrong man is to keepe poſſeſsion of his ſtrength: but touching the vſe of our goods, we muſt doe as hath beene ſaide. And if it pleaſe God to humble vs with pouertie, then thoſe that haue more then an Homer full, that is to ſay, more then they neede, they muſt then doe the like for vs. If they did reſerue of their Manna it did ſtinke, it did them no good, Exod. 16. 20. it was full of wormes: ſo when men reſerue couetouſly more then needes, Theeues, as Chriſt ſaith, breake thorough and ſteale, the ruſt eates their coyne, the moath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes their garments: not but that among the Iewes ſome had more wealth then ſome other: for the elder brother was to haue a double portion: but becauſe he did maintaine more in his familie then did his younger brother, in the ende all came to one reckoning. When in the Lord his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20972:29"/> praier the rich make this petition, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi> they pray not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for themſelues, but for their poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. But when they haue meanes in their hand to releeue them, and doe it not, how then can they be ſaid truly to make this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition? For as a man that praieth for his owne foode, if he vſe not the meanes, he may truly be ſaid to tempt God: ſo when a man deſires the Lord to relieue his poore brethren, and God hauing put meanes into his hands to relieue them withall, and yet he will not imploy them, what doth he els but dally with the Lord? And we are to conſider that this bountifulnes that is here ſpoken of, is to be vnderſtood of the Saints that doe now liue, leaſt imagining them onely to be Saints that are dead, we doe as the Papiſts doe, who in the ſcarſitie of all things, had their dead imagined ſaints clad and couered with golde, ſilke garments, pretious iewells, hauing waxe candles ſet before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within &amp; without the church at noone daies, when many true Saints of God had no ſuccour beſtowed vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20972:29"/>
            <q>
               <p>16 <hi>And thanks be vnto God which hath put in the heart of Titus the ſame care for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>17. <hi>Becauſe he accepted the exhortation, yea he was ſo carefull, that of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord he went vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>To mooue the Corinthians to relieue their brethren, he tells them what excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men God raiſed vp to deale in this matter with them: and as before he accounted it a grace to giue, ſo doth he now account it a grace to ſtirre vp to giuing. Men are loth to deale in ſuch a matter as men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are hardly drawne to performe: and a man of a good diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if he hath wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, had rather giue all out of his owne purſe, then to be troubled with ſuch a kind of buſineſſe, if dutie did not mooue him thereunto. What a tedious piece of work is it for a man to gather that which men are rated at, notwithſtanding they cannot chuſe but account it as due debt that which they are ſet at: how loath may men then be thought to be to part from that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they thinke that they haue more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20972:30"/> It is the Lord without whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence not ſo much as a ſparrow light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon the ground. He hath a worke in euery mans minde as it pleaſeth him. VVhen Apollos was requeſted to goe to the Corinthians, he had no minde to goe at that time, 1. Cor. 16. 12. The Lord might haue diſpoſed ſo in like manner of the heart of Titus. But in that the Lord did otherwiſe diſpoſe of his heart, they muſt needes ſee that it came of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were to yeelde to the motion of Titus in this matter, Gen. 24, 50. As the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tels the Galathians, that they were not to doe as they did, becauſe it came not of God, Gal. 5. 8. Iames 3. 6. So they were to yeeld to Titus, becauſe God ſtirred him vp in this duty. And he thankes God for it: for the good workes of the ſeruants of god ſhould cauſe vs to glorify our father which is in heauen, &amp; is the author of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Mat. 5. 16. Titus was mooued by mem, but it was the Lord which put into his heart to yeeld to the exhortation. And we are to marke, the exhortation and the worke
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20972:30"/> of God his ſpirit are ioyned together. 17. He is ſaid to be very ready of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord without any great hailing therevnto, And yet as there is no matter be it neuer ſo ready to take fire, that can be ſet on fire, be put to it: no though a man be ready to every good worke, yet he had need to be exhorted therevnto: and the Lord accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of it when by exhortation we are brought vnto duty, Heb. 11. 11. Act. 16. 14. The readines which was in Titus to come is worthy of obſeruation: for commonly our hearts are like paper oyled, that hardly receiueth the print of the pen. Fire is the thing whereby we diſpatch moſt of our buſines in our houſes, and a ſlacke fire doth hinder our matters greatly: ſo doth a ſlack affection about any duty. And it was to great purpoſe to tell the Corinthes howe willing Titus was to come vnto them: for it was a ſigne that he had a good liking of them A man is loth to go to a place where he thinkes he ſhall not be welcome. It is hope which ſets a man a worke to goe to any place: It is that which lifteth vp their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20972:31"/> feete to goe any iourney, which was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good meanes to make them anſwere that good exhortation which he had of them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>18 <hi>And we haue alſo ſent with him the brother, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpell throughout all the Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>19 And not ſo onely, <hi>But is alſo choſen of the churches to be a fellow in our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, concerning this grace that is ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vs vnto the glory of the ſame Lord, and declaration of your prompt minde.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>18 Barnabas is the party that he ſpeakes of Act. 11. 30. whoſe praiſe was in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpell. For not onely the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but the preaching of the Goſpell, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the goſpell, Rom. 2. 16. Gal. 3. 1. becauſe it is a meanes to make them giue more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, when they ſee that ſuch are the collectours as will certenly deliuer it to the parties to whome it is giuen: therefore he meaneth theſe excellent men. And to the ende that they might not doubt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery of that which was giuen, he tels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that thoſe ſhall go with it whom they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20972:31"/> ſhall appoint, 1. 16. 3. Diuers will not giue, though they be neuer ſo faithfull which are appointed the diſtributers of it; they are wont to alleadge that they will giue it themſelues where they thinke meete. But if euery man ſhould doe ſo, what a confuſion would there be? And we ſee how the poore are forced to ſteale, and to beg, when euery one that ſhould giue is left in this manner to his owne deuotion. For this is a true ſaying, that which all men regard, no man regardes. But when there be parties appointed fit for the purpoſe, then the poore ſhall be regarded. Men are wont to alleadge, that they meane to giue more then all the world ſhall be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withall: but indeede the truth is, that none giue leſſe priuately then thoſe that draw backe in a publique collection. The thing which Chriſt reprooueth Matth. 6. is, when men giue priuately to be ſeene of men they will doe it in ſuch manner as all the world muſt know it: ſuch boaſting in deede is like the cackling of an henne, who when ſhee hath laide an egge euery bodie
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20972:32"/> muſt know what a worthie act ſhee hath done. But otherwiſe for a man to giue as his neighbours doe, in a publike collection vpon a publike agreement, this is not to blow a trumpet before him when he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his almes: and if he meanes to giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further reliefe priuately, he may doe it as cloſely and as ſecretly as he doth deſire. Chriſt doth not condemne, but he doth greatly allow the fact of the poore widow that in a publike collection ſhewed her forwardnes, in giuing as others did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, and more franckly (conſidering her poore eſtate) then any of the reſt. 19 He, the ambaſſadour I meane, that was to goe with the money, was not onely commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for preaching, but he was accounted wiſe and faithfull, and therefore fit for this preſent buſines. As much therefore as they did detract from this buſines and miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo much did they detract from the glorie of God, and from the declaration of their readie minde that was ſought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For according to the greatnes of thoſe which were to goe vpon that ambaſſage,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20972:32"/> they might well gather of the greatnes of the matter that was to be dealt in, and of that great deſire they had to haue the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage to take place, Numb. 22. 15. This wiſdom in appointing ſuch excellent men, as it is to be followed in many things, ſo is it to be followed when men make their Wills. For let me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giue neuer ſo large lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, yet if there be failing in the execution, all comes to nothing. The children which are to be fatherleſſe, commonly are left to the curteſie of thoſe which haue iittle affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to them, but to that which they haue: &amp; haue by vertue of their executor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip moſt knowledge and oppertunity to ſpoile them, <hi>ovem lupo,</hi> or it may be ſaide of them that they commit the geeſe to the keeping of the foxe. By marking through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whether men deale iuſtly and truely in their affaires, they ſhall knowe whether they be meete men to be their executors.</p>
            <q>
               <p>20 <hi>Avoiding this, that no man ſhould blame vs in this aboundance that is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered by vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>21 <hi>Prouiding for honeſt things, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20972:33"/> before the Lord, but alſo before men.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>What his meaning is, we may ſee 1. Cor. 16. 3. for there he ſaith, <hi>whome ſoeuer ye ſhall allow by letters, them will I ſend to bring your liberalitie to Ieruſalem.</hi> The Apoſtle himſelfe was deſired to carry this money, but he would not be alone in this buſines: but he would haue witneſſes that the money was faithfully beſtowed. He which refuſeth to offer himſelfe to triall in ſuch a matter, may well be ſuſpected. It is but a vaine thing to ſay god knowes my heart, when I may make my truth and ſimplicity known alſo vnto men. When men haue any authority ouer thoſe to whome they are to approoue themſelues, then they are wont to diſdaine to approue their doings vnto their conſciences. But if Paul that had the authority of an Apoſtle, might ſtand vpon his own bare credit for the faithfull deliuery of that he was betru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted withall, better then any man in the world how dare any the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times be rather ſuſpected then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſtand ſo vpon their own bare word,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20972:33"/> that no man may be ſo bold as to ſay vnto them, how haue you beſtowed the mony that you were betruſted withall. We are to conſider of this the rather, becauſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the goodnes of God, we are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a reaſonable order for prouiding for the poore. If thoſe that haue the mony in their handes doe not from time to time very carefully, as much as they may, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue themſelues to the conſciences of thoſe whoſe money they haue receiued, it is to be feared, that in a little time all will come to nothing: and therefore this is one of the things that muſt as ſtrictly be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as any other thing whatſoeuer that belongeth to this buſines. And therefore I beſeech thoſe in the feare of God, that haue and are to haue the mony that is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in their handes, as they loue their owne credit, and as they delight that men ſhould be encouraged to the dutie of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that the poore Saints of God may be relieued, that they would cauſe their ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie this waies to be ſo ſeen, that he that runneth may read it, as the Prophet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20972:34"/> Men can not be too carefull of this dutie: and therefore if they did cauſe to be drawne in a table what euery man doth giue, &amp; what euery poore man receiueth, and cauſed euery ſuch table to be ſet vpon euery church dore throughout the town, it were a very ſimple and ſyncere and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable order. The keeping of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerplus in their hands to relieue according as extraordinarie occaſion ſhall fall out, wil marre all, except the people whoſe money it is doe like of this order, and ſee as plainly how this ouerplus is beſtowed as well as the other that is ordinarily beſtowed. All executors may learne a good leſſon from hence: they thinke they are not bound to pay any legacies, except men aske it them: notwithſtanding it falleth out many times, that men know not whether they haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing giuen them or no: or it may be they knowe not the time when it is due. And all that haue to deale with receiuing of money, haue here a notable example gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them by the Apoſtle. Men are woont to flie to the report of ſuch, as either know
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20972:34"/> not their doings, or els will not ſpeake rightly of them. But the Apoſtle prouided that no man might thinke otherwiſe then well of him. He had before his eyes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually the comming of Chriſt, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to haue a cleare conſcience both towards God and towardes men, Act. 24. verſ. 16.</p>
            <q>
               <p>22 <hi>And vve haue ſent with them our brother, whome vve haue oftentimes proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be diligent in many things: but now much more diligent, for the great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I haue in you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>It is as we haue heard, to great purpoſe, to know who be the parties which ſhall diſtribute that which is giuen: for it will incourage men the rather to giue. If men ſhall diſtribute it at leiſure they knowe not when, this will cauſe men to haue little minde to giue. He muſt therefore be quick and round and readie in his office that is this waies to be imployed. Men had neede to giue good attendance vpon thoſe that are to giue, or els their affection will coole quickly: and the poore that ſhould haue
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20972:35"/> that which is giuen, can not forbeare it any long time. So that the diligence the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh of we ſee is very neceſſarie. And he doth put them in good hope of the partie whome he doth commmend, becauſe he had experience of his diligence in the like affaires: and he doth aſſure them that they may now much more looke for the like diligence, becauſe of that forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that he did not doubt to be in them. For ſeeing he was diligent when he had to doe with a backward people, he knew that it would doe him good to be diligent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould haue to doe with ſuch a forward people. Men commonly appoint ſuch col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours for the poore as are of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wealth; but to appoint ſuch as will ſtay the dealings of their owne priuate affaires to attend vpon this publike worke, that will inquire who be ſicke, or who haue more ſpeciall neede, and that will euery manner of way beſtirre themſelues in this worke, this is the thing that is not once thought vpon.</p>
            <q>
               <p>23 <hi>Whether any doe inquire of Titus, he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20972:35"/> is my fellow and helper to you ward: or of our brethren, they are meſſengers of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and of the glorie of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>24 <hi>Wherefore ſhew towards them, and before the Churches the proofe of your loue, and of the reioycing that we haue of you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>That which the Apoſtle did ſpeake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of thoſe three excellent men in a large manner, adding other matters in the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of them in. Now to the end that they might the rather be mooued with their excellencie, he ſpeakes of them altogether without the mingling of any other matter in the ſpeaking of them, that their minde might not be diſtracted; but that it might wholly be taken vp with thinking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Concerning Titus, he reports of him that he was his fellow and helper, and that to them ward. They were yoked together as it were in one and in the ſelf ſame work. If therefore they made any reckoning of the Apoſtle himſelfe, then they muſt needs thinke well of Titus, whome the Apoſtle made choice of to be his companion in ſo great a worke. And he working in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20972:36"/> worke of the miniſterie amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they neede no other witneſſes to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue of him but themſelues: for he was the Apoſtles fellowe and helper to them ward. As for the other brethren, they are the meſſengers not of particular men, but of whole Churches. If therefore the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the churches be of account with them, they muſt then regard that teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that is giuen vnto them. 24 He doth therfore infer this vpon his former ſpeach, namely that that which is done before them, is done before al the churches. They were to the churches as committies be to the Parliament houſe. The whole orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the matter was committed to their fidelitie. If in the mouth of two or three witneſſes euery word ſhould ſtand, how much more ought it to ſtand in the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of whole churches. The churches are of the counſell of Chriſt, Ioh. 15. 15. and we know that a meſſenger comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any one of the Counſell is greatly to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of, but comming from the whole bodie of the Counſell he is much more to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20972:36"/> be eſteemed. He would haue them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conſider, that in theſe meſſengers they had to doe with all the churches: and when they were before them, they were before all the Churches, who looked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to giue teſtimonie how they ſtood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the relieuing of the poore Saints of Ieruſalem. To this end he maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glorie of Chriſt: for if one man be the image and glorie of God; if the Lord will haue his glorie ſhine forth in the preheminence of any one Chriſtian, how much more is his glorie repreſented vnto vs in the ambaſſadours of whol chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, 1. Cor. 11. 7. When any one of the poore members of Chriſt are offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, Chriſt himſelfe preſents himſelfe then vnto vs, as Math. 25. But here he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe after a more glorious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The Lord doth as it were glorie in his faithfull ſeruants. <hi>Haſt thou conſidered my ſeruant Iob,</hi> ſaith the Lord vnto ſatan, Iob. 1. Such excellent men are thoſe that are here me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. They were ſuch as would glorifie Chriſt for any good worke that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20972:37"/> they ſaw in any of his ſeruants.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_commentary">
            <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
            <q>
               <p>1 <hi>For as touching the miniſtring to the Saints, it is ſuperfluous for me to write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 <hi>For I knovv your readines of minde, whereof I boaſt my ſelfe of you vnto them of Macedonia, and ſay, that Achaia vvas prepared a yeere ago, and your zeale hath prouoked many.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The vſe of writing is to certifie the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to whome he doth write, of that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is either ignorant, or els had neede to be ſtirred vp vnto: but in neither of theſe reſpects was there any cauſe wherefore he ſhould write to the Corinthians: therfore he ſaith touching the miniſtring to the Saints that it was ſuperfluous for him to write vnto them, yet becauſe he had giuen forth euery where to other churches how forward the Corinthians were; and by boaſting thus of them he had as it were entred into bonds for their forwardnes. In
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20972:37"/> this reſpect it was meete that he ſhould put them in minde of this matter. He vſeth a certaine kinde of ſpeach called <hi>praeteritio:</hi> for he ſaith, that <hi>it is ſuperfluous for him to write,</hi> and yet he writeth. His meaning is, that it was ſuperfluous to ſtand long vpon this matter in writing. He doth graunt that they were readie enough of their owne accord, and neede not to be ſtirred vp by writing; yet becauſe he had boaſted ſo confidently of them, and did thereby as it were enter into bonds in their behalfe; in this reſpect he dealeth as one that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into bonds for another. And in ſuch a caſe though a man thinks well of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for whome he is bound, and doubts not but that he will pay the debt, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the forgetting of ſuch a matter would be exceeding dangerous to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie himſelfe, and to the partie that was bound for him: the conſideration of the greatnes of the daunger, will cauſe him to put the partie in minde of the debt, though otherwiſe he would ſay nothing. He calls the gift of the Corinths a miniſtring to the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20972:38"/> Saints, giuing them thereby to vnderſtand, that they are but ſtewards to beſtow the riches of God that he hath betruſted them withall, 1. Pet. 4. 10. The Lord had giuen him his riches as it were by a letter of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, to giue where neede was. 2 Leaſt the Corinthians ſhould thinke much of the commendation that he gaue of the Macedonians, as if he had made the Corinthians no bodie in reſpect of them: or as if he had diſcredited them vnto thoſe of Macedonia, he telleth them that he was ſo farre from it, that he did boaſt of them vnto thoſe of Macedonia. And as he took an occaſion to ſtirre vp the Corinths by the example of the Macedonians, ſo did he in like manner ſtirre vp the Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by the forwardnes of the Corinthians. Corinthum was in Achaia. The Apoſtle would not haue ſpoken ſo of them, except he had ſeene ſome good forwardnes in them. Companie makes euen a dull beaſt to goe faſter: and therefore the Apoſtle is much in prouoking by examples. And here we ſee how wiſely the Apoſtle dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20972:38"/> with the churches of God. We ſee in both theſe epiſtles how plainly he doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue the Corinthians, and yet when he ſpeakes to the Macedonians of them, he ſaith that Achaia was prepared a yeare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe: ſo that as he commended the Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians to the Corinthians for that they had alreadie done, ſo doth he commend the Corinths for that they were prepared for to doe. And here we may ſee the right manner of dealing with the churches of God. When we are to deale with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, we are to open vnto them their wants moſt faithfully: but when we are to ſpeake to others of them, we are then to commend that that is good in them. To encourage Titus that was to goe amongſt the Corinthians, he ſpeakes reuerently of them. <hi>If,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>I haue boaſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nything to Titus of you, I haue not beene aſhamed: for our boaſting vvas true.</hi> But when he dealeth with themſelues, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he giues God thanks for that good that was amongſt them, yet doth he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſh them, 2. Cor. 7. 14. We ſee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20972:39"/> how the Apoſtle doth mooue by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others: and therefore when we haue an example of ſtrangers that dwell in our owne kingdome, we are very bad ſchollers if we learne nothing by them: their poore are well ſet a worke, none of them goeth a begging: they goe ſweete and cleane, ſo that they may be admitted into any honeſt companie.</p>
            <q>
               <p>3 <hi>Now I haue ſent the brethren, least our reioycing ouer you ſhould be in vaine in this behalfe, that ye as I haue ſaide be readie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4 <hi>Leaſt if they of Macedonia come with me, and find you vnprepared: we, (I need not to ſay you) ſhould be aſhamed in this my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant boaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5 <hi>Wherefore I thought it neceſſarie to exhort the brethren to come before vnto you, and to finiſh your benevolence appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, that it might be readie and come as of benenolence, and not of ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>3 Before we heard what hope he had of them, now he doth ioyne a godly feare
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20972:39"/> to this his hope: <hi>res eſt ſolliciti plenati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moris amor.</hi> Howſoeuer the ſuſpition and feare that is voide of loue, is condemned in the ſcripture, 2. Sam. 10. 3. yet that ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie that is ioyned with loue, and that doth ſtirre vs vp to dutie and watchfulnes ouer thoſe towards whome we carrie this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ielouſie, is greatly commended in the ſcripture, 2. Corinth. 11. 2. Iob 1. 5. <hi>It may be,</hi> ſaith Iob, <hi>that my ſonnes haue ſinned.</hi> Shame we know is a caſting downe of the minde, and leaueth it voide of all comfort to ſupport it ſelfe withall. The feare of this ſhame made Ezra rather chooſe to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard life and goods and all that he had, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then he would bring vpon himſelfe this ſhame, Ezr. 9. 22. This ſhame cauſed him that he would not aske any helpe of the King to whome before he had ſaide, <hi>The hand of our good Goa ſhall be vpon vs vvithout any ſuch helpe from man.</hi> To preuent therefore this ſo vncomfortable a thing, he thought it good to ſend the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren before-hande to prepare them, leaſt that thoſe of Macedonia finding
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20972:40"/> them vnprepared they ſhould be aſhamed.</p>
            <q>
               <p>6 <hi>This yet remember, that he vvhich ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reape alſo ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and he which ſoweth liberally ſhall reape alſo liberally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7 <hi>As euery man wiſheth in his heart, ſo let him giue, not grudgingly, or of neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for God loueth a chearefull giuer.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>6 To mooue them the rather vnto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie, he doth liken it vnto ſowing, and he tells them that as the husband doth not thinke that his ſeede is loſt when he doth ſcatter it into the ground, but that he ſhall gaine greatly by it: and therefore he will not ſow ſparingly, leaſt he ſhould haue but a thinne harueſt, but he will ſow as much as he is able that he may reape according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He telleth them that the caſe ſo ſtandeth in giuing. The hope that the husbandman hath of his harueſt cauſeth him to breake vp his ground to fallow it, and to twy fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, and to ſow it, and to harrow it: and all this paines is taken in hope of a good harueſt: for harueſt is that that promiſeth great ioy vnto them: in ſo much that that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20972:40"/> great ioy that is brought vnto vs by Chriſt Ieſus, is likened to the ioy in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, Eſai 9. 3. 7 He telleth them in what manner they ſhould giue, as a man wiſheth in his heart. A man muſt not tarrie till the time of collection doth come, and then to giue as ſhall come into his minde: but as in all other duties, ſo in this he muſt purpoſe before hande what he meaneth to doe: <hi>Dum in dubio eſt animus paulo huc atque illuc impellitur:</hi> and therefore men are willed with purpoſe of heart to cleane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, Act. 11. 23. And therefore we read that Daniel determined before he came to the triall what he meant to doe, Dan. 1. 8. He would not haue them giue as of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, his meaning is not but that we ſhould inioyne our ſelues of neceſsitie to ſerue God, as in all other dutie, ſo in this. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue a naughtie nature that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all dutie, therefore ought we to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence and to force our ſelues to doe well. But when a man ſhall giue by reaſon of that opinion that his neighbours would otherwiſe haue of him, deſiring in the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20972:41"/> meane time to haue ſpared it, if by any meanes this might haue ſtoode with the ſauing of his credit: to giue of neceſsitie in this manner is that that is here condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: he mooueth vs therefore to cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in giuing, by telling vs that God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a chearefull giuer. The loue of God is ſo comfortable a thing, that it is able to ſweeten the moſt ſowre receipts of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and therefore the Apoſtle tells men that they ſhould hold themſelues very wel contented with affliction, becauſe it is an argument of his loue. Whome God doth once loue he doth alwaies loue: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his vnchangeable decree is deſcribed by louing of Iacob, Rom. 9. The ende of giuing is to cheare the parties to whome we doe giue: when a man therefore ſhall giue a thing in ſuch maner, as if he thought the partie to whom he doth giue vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of it, then the end of giuing is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. When men ſhall giue a gift with their hand, and call it backe againe with their ſpeach or countenance, this takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the comfort of the gift: <hi>gratia ab offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20972:41"/> quodmor a tardat abeſt.</hi> He that is vnder, may ſoone thinke that he is deſpiſed and accounted a burden to the world. Men therefore ſhould giue in ſuch manner as all ſuch thoughts may be kept from them. When men haue neuer a word with them which may perſwade their geſtes that they are welco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, it makes their cheere a great deale leſſe then it ſhould be: for it is a true ſaying, that welcome and the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof is the beſt cheere. Howe therefore was the father in the entertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his ſonne, he brought forth the robe, he put rings on his fingers, he cauſed a fat calfe to be killed, come ſaith he let vs eate and be merry. It is reported of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull man that he was wont to ſay to the parties to whome he gaue any thing, I am as willing to giue it as any man is to take it. How cheereful was Lidia in entertayning of the Apoſtle: If ſaith ſhee, you thinke that I am faithfull to the Lord, then come into my houſe and make account that I make reckoning of the company of the ſeruants of god. Thus ſhee conſtrained them to eate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20972:42"/> of her meat, Act. 16. 15. How comfortably did Abraham entertaine his geſts, he did runne to meete them, that they might ſee how welcome they ſhould be vnto him, though he knew them not, and therefore could looke for no benefit from them. The Lord would make Abraham a patterne of this cheerefulneſſe: and therefore though the angels which he ſent vnto him, ſtood not in any neede of his meate: yet to take a triall what comfortable entertaynment he would giue vnto them, he offers them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in ſuch a manner as if they had ſtood in neede of his entertainment. So in like manner the Lord could giue euery man enough to liue of himſelfe if pleaſed him and that with as little coſt or trouble to him, as if he gaue him nothing. But becauſe his meaning is to take a triall how well and louingly men will beſtowe their goodes: he doth therefore offer his ſeruants in their wants vnto them Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſidered that theſe men were weary in their iourney, that their feete were weary with their trauell, eſpecially trauelling in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20972:42"/> the heate of the day, Gen. 18. 1. 7. To refreſh them that waies he offers them water for their feete, and a coole feare to ſit in vnder a greene tree that they might reſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and becauſe he ſaw their hearts nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be comforted after their trauell, he tels them that they ſhall haue a little bread to comfort them that waies. His meaning was to make them good cheere, but leaſt that the feare of putting him to too much coſt ſhould ſtay them from comming in vnto him as it ſtaied Dauid from going to Abſolon, 2. Sam. 13. 25. He therefore onely maketh mention of a little bread: and he doth reaſon with them from the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, that God his meaning was that they ſhould come into his houſe, and therefore he gaue them occaſion to come that waies. We ſee how courteouſly he behaued himſelfe towardes them as if he had beene beholding to them and not they to him for comming into his houſe. It is a rare thing not to be ſomwhat inſolent, and to thinke that they may ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ouer looke the parties to whome
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20972:43"/> they haue giuen entertainment diſdaining in the meane time to take the like enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment at their handes vpon the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. Nowithſtanding the Apoſtle would haue it to be made mutuall and ſo conſequently cherefull cheerfull, 1. Pet. 4. 9. For it taketh libertie away from a man when he hath to deale with thoſe which are otherwiſe his equalls, if there be refuſall to haue the entertainment mutuall. Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham makes mention to his geſts onely of a little bread, but he goeth in to his wife and wills her to make ready with all the ſpeed that might be fiue cakes, and he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed butter, and milke, and veale to be brought in before them: he would not ſay to his gueſts you fare not ſo wel euery day at home; but he makes little of that which he ſet before them: he ſtandes by them to beare them company, for it appeares he had dined before they came. This cherful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is highly commended by Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus, and is more regarded then the meate it ſelfe, Luke, 7. 44. For though the Phariſe ſet meate before Chriſt, yet becauſe he vſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20972:43"/> no cheerefulneſſe in entertaining of him: he therefore magnifieth the poore woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before him &amp; ſaith, <hi>I entred into thy houſe and thou gaueſt me no water for my feete, thou gauest me no kiſſe, thou didſt not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint my head with oyle as ſhee hath done.</hi> Thus we ſee howe and why the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a cheerefull giuer, and that if we will haue aſſurance that God doth loue vs, which loue of his is the cauſe of all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits which we receiue from him, then may we giue cherefully.</p>
            <q>
               <p>8 <hi>And God is able to make all grace to abound towards you, that you alwaies ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all ſufficiency in all things, may abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in euery good worke.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The cauſe of the vncheerefulneſſe in the giuer, is becauſe he feareth himſelfe ſhould want; the Apoſtle tels them that God is of tha power, that they neede not feare any ſuch matter, but that they ſhal haue enough both for themſelues and others. The cauſe of all error is becauſe men doe not beleeue the ſcripture, nor the power of God, as Chriſt telleth the Saduces: he doth firſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20972:44"/> therefore commend the power of God vnto them, and afterward the ſcriptures. The principall proppe that Abraham had to vphold his faith, was to perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he which promiſed was able alſo to performe. In all the articles of our faith, it is moſt neceſſarie that we ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the power of God, for how ſhal we beleeue that God made heauen and earth, that Chriſt was borne of a virgin, but by beleuing that the power of the higheſt did ouerſhadow her: the like may be ſaid of all the other articles of our faith. We hauing therefore the ſame word of god to warrant that which the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh of; why ſhould we not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the one as well as the other. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Apoſtle is not to reaſon onely from the power of god as the Papiſts doe when they would make vs beleeue that the bread in the ſacrament is turned into the body of Chriſt, becauſe god is able to make it ſo, for Chriſt could haue turned ſtones into bread as Satan would haue had him to haue done, but he would not do it:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20972:44"/> ſo that although it be a good argument to reaſon from the power of god, when we are already certified of his willingnes in the thing, yet when we cannot be perſwaded of his willingnes in a thing, it is in vaine to ſpeake of his power. The ſcripture telleth vs that it is not the will of god, to haue his body to be made of a peece of bread that the heauens muſt hold him vntill his ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comming. The word of god telleth vs, that all the miracles that Chriſt wrought, they were apparent to the outward ſenſes of men, in ſo much that they were aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and ſaid we neuer ſawe the like in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. In that therefore there is no ſuch thing ſene in the ſacrament, it is plaine that there is no tranſubſtantiation; but in a thouſand places we are taught that god will aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompence the liberall perſon. We ſee therefore that the reaſon of the Apoſtle is good, although the reaſons of the Popiſh Church be not good: the Lord is able to fill them will all ſufficiency, for he is called the god of all ſufficient. By ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency he doth not meane that they ſhall
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20972:45"/> haue that which is ſufficient for their own vſe, which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding is a great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God to ſoule and bodie. For we ſee how many torment themſelues that haue not a contented minde: they are neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, for <hi>he that loueth ſiluer ſhall neuer be ſatisfied with ſiluer,</hi> as Eccleſiaſtes ſaith, neither ſhall ſuch haue any vſe of that they haue, Eccleſiaſtes 5. 9. On the other ſide, he whoſe heart God filleth with ſufficiencie, hath as much ioy continually as any other man hath, for that little time he is at a feaſt, Prov. 15. 15. For the Lord therefore to giue vs a contented minde, is a great benefit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in reſpect of our owne priuate vſe. But the ſufficiencie that is here ſpoken of is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to giue to others, as appeares by the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the verſe, by which words we may alſo ſee to what ende we ſhould vſe that ſufficiencie that the Lord hath giuen vs, namly to abound in euery good work. We ſee what good thoughts be in the hearts of the ſeruants of God, when God giueth them aboundance in reſpect of the thoughts that be in the mindes of wicked
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20972:45"/> men in their aboundance. <hi>Is not this great Babel,</hi> ſaith Nabuchadnezzar, <hi>that I haue built,</hi> Dan. 4. 27. Hamon bragged that he was promoted aboue the princes of the King, Eſter 4. 11. <hi>Soule, ſoule, take thy reſt,</hi> ſaith the rich man, Luk. 12. 19. But what ſaith Dauid after his glorious victories, <hi>what an indignitie is it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I ſhould dwell in an houſe of Cedar, and that the arke of God ſhould remain in curtaines,</hi> 2. Sam. 7. 2. <hi>Is there any left of Sauls houſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I may ſhew kindnes vnto him for Ionathans ſake,</hi> 2. Sam. 9. 1. He ſent to all the places where he had beene entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 2. Sam. 30. 26. We muſt not beſtow a litle and the worſt of our goods vpon the poore and vpon good vſes, but our firſt fruits, or the chiefe of our goods, Prov. 3. 9. Exod. 34. 26. Gen. 4. 4. the fatteſt muſt be beſtowed vpon the ſeruice of god, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lach. 3. 10. Worldly minded men that are onely giuen to getting, when they ſhould entertaine ſtraungers which haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to come to towne, thinke the time loſt that is ſpent that waies, and that ſuch
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20972:46"/> matters ſhould not be ſtoode vpon: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>giue your ſelues to hoſpitalitie,</hi> Rom. 12. 13. And why ſhould men thinke that the beſtowing of time about the well vſing of their goods, ſhould not be much more acceptable vnto God, then the getting of them, eſpecially ſeeing the Scripture whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſpeaketh of the getting of them, it ſaith. <hi>vſe the world as if you vſed it not,</hi> 1. Cor. 7. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſpeaks of the well imployment of them it ſaith, <hi>giue your ſelues thereunto, be not forgetful of it,</hi> Ebr. 13. 2.</p>
            <q>
               <p>9 <hi>As it is written, He hath ſparſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and hath giuen to the poore: his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence remaineth for euer.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The Apoſtle prooueth the truth of that which he had affirmed in the former verſe, namely that thoſe which giue ſhall haue wherewithall to giue ſtill. He doth prooue it by the ſcripture. The ſcripture is ſo certen a thing, that if any that hath liued amongſt vs, with whome we haue beene very well acquainted, ſhould riſe from the dead, and tel vs from the experience of that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20972:46"/> which he had ſeene, that vnmercifull rich men are tormented in fire, yet ſhould we beleeue the ſcripture a thouſand times more then his report. <hi>They haue the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Moſes and the Puophets,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if they beleeue not them, neither will they beleeue though one riſe from the dead,</hi> Luk. 16. The Church of Rome doth goe about to leſſon the authoritie of this argument, by ſaying that if any make a queſtion about the meaning of any place of Scripture, then the ſcripture muſt not be iudge in this caſe, but the Church. But we read in the 4. of Matthew, that when Satan abuſed the ſcripture and ſaide, <hi>It is written, He ſhall giue his angels charge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee, that thou daſh not thy foot againſt a ſtone,</hi> that Chriſt did not flie to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any other, but makes the ſcripture alone of it ſelfe to iuſtifie and to vphold it ſelfe: <hi>It is written,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God. He that giueth to the poore,</hi> ſaith Salomon, <hi>lendeth vnto the Lord.</hi> The Lord giues them a bill of his hand that he will ſee them paide with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20972:47"/> And it is a ſtraunge caſe that men will beleeue euery meane man vpon a bill of his hand, and yet the Lord as if he were a bankerout, when he offers his bill it will not be taken. The bleſsings that the Lord hath beſtowed already vpon the rich, in making them as it were the elder brothers ſhould make them to be good to their yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brothers. But this becauſe it is blacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, the Lord will not ſtand vpon it: &amp; becauſe in any caſe he would haue them prouided for, he is content to enter into bondes, and to become ſurety for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. The poore are the men that we ſhould giue vnto: for howeſoeuer rich friends may feaſt one another ſometimes, yet our vſuall feaſting ſhould be for the poore, Luk. 14. 12. We being much giuen to outward things, becauſe bidding of the poore hath not ſo much ſhewe nor glorie in it as hath the bidding of the rich, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are wont to delight more in the one then in the other. But if we ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we muſt avoide the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and the pride of life, and that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20972:47"/> thoſe things which are highly accounted of amongſt men, are abhominable vnto god: then we ſhall be of another minde: <hi>giue ſtrong arinke vnto him that is readie to periſh,</hi> Prov. 31. ſaith Salomon. We muſt bid the poore to our houſes notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingour collection money: for there was a collection in Chriſt his time, Marke, 12. 43. And yet we are taught that we ſhould bid the poore, the blinde, and the lame; many be the things which may incourage vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this duty. In reſpect of God, he liketh beſt of thoſe duties which are done to our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without hauing any reſpect vnto our ſelues, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are done with a ſingle eye, not to rebound vpon our ſelues. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect alſo of the poore, it muſt needes be more comfortable to them, then to other gueſtes: for it may be they eate not one good meale in a moneth, and the full diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an honyco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, but to the hungry man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſowre thing is ſweete. It will helpe men alſo againſt that diſdaine which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in men, for when we admit them to eate at our table, it is a token that we doe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20972:48"/> not diſdaine them. It is a meanes to ſtirre vp our ſelues otherwiſe to be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: for when we ſee nothing but plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, when we heare of nothing but plentie, it is an hard matter then to conſider of the eſtate of poore men: but when we ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and talke with them, if it be done warily without vpbraiding of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their poore eſtate, then are we beſides feeding of them, otherwiſe comfortable vnto them, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not brought vp as we haue beene, they cannot tell howe to apply themſelues in their ſpeech vnto vs, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould we apply our ſelues vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We muſt conſider that as no other duty, ſo is not this pleaſant vnto our nature, but when Chriſt commandeth it, that ſhould make it pleaſant: If we would conſider that euery duty doth conſiſt the denying of our ſelues, then we ſhall eaſily ſee that this pleaſeth God better then the beeing in more delightfull company: and it ſhould make it delightfull, when we conſider that thoſe that doe thus, Chriſt will ſet them downe at his table, he good himſelfe and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20972:48"/> in his own perſon attend vpon them, Luk. 1237. his meaning is that he wil giue them moſt comfortable entertainment. It remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth now to ſpeake of the ende, for the which this teſtimony of ſcripture was eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially alleadged by the Apoſtle, namely to aſſure thoſe which giue, that they ſhall haue wherewithall to giue ſtill. And we may ſee the truth of this, as it were by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration: when rich men be much in bidding one another, it asketh great expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for they looke for a ſumpteous enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment being accuſtomed to a plentifull diet at home: but the poore beeing acquain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with a meane diet, a little prouiſion wil content them: ſo that by this meanes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the exceſſe of riot which is wont to be by reaſon of the great variety of diſhes, and length of time great charges are alſo preuented. When men bidde their rich friendes, they are wont to ſet out their wealth &amp; their port with plate and other furniture, as he did of whome we reade in the firſt of Heſter, to ſhewe the glory of his kingdome. Al theſe thinges be avoided
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20972:49"/> by bidding of the poore, ſo that men ſhall be able to bidde them ſtill, that their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence may remaine for euer: neither ſhal they onely haue wherewithall to giue, but they alſo ſhall haue a minde &amp; a good will to giue, which is as great a gift as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can wiſh to he in a man. A man is in no requeſt which is not ready to binde others vnto him by kindneſſe. Kindnes to other giftes is as the face to other parts of the bodie: This kindnes alſo is vnto all other gifts, as the ſpirit is vnto the body; for it is the life and moouer of them, for otherwiſe they be as dead in our ſelues. Onely by kindnes are they conueyed to others, euen iuſtice it ſelfe without this bountifulneſſe is as an handſome: and comely body is that hath a crabbed face vpon it; euen the withered vine tree is more regarded then is theſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oke, becauſe of the goodneſſe thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <p>11 <hi>Alſo he that findeth ſeede to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, will miniſter likewiſe bread for food, and multiply your ſeede, and increaſe the fruits of your beneuolence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>12 <hi>That on all partes you may be made
<pb facs="tcp:20972:49"/> rich vnto all liberallitie, which cauſeth through vs thankſgiuing vnto god.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>10 He confirmes his former ſpeech an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering an obiection; for it might be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that there is not the like reaſon of the poore, that their is of the feild, for the one is not ſo yeelding as is the other: he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs therefore that it is god that cauſeth the earth to be thus yeldable: &amp; we hauing the promiſe of god that he will cauſe that to be as yeeldable vnto vs, as that is which is ſcattered vpon the earth, is as mightie &amp; as willing to performe it the one way as the other. Whether we vnderſtand the ſpeech in wiſhing manner, that God will miniſter foode, or whether it be ſet down as a promiſe, it is not materiall: for we muſt pray for nothing, but for that for the which we haue a promiſe: and if we haue a promiſe for any thing, we may be bould to pray for it, and we are ſure that we ſhall haue it. As the Lord therefore doth giue to the husbandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſoweth his grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not onely that which is ſufficient for the maintenance of his family, but he giueth
<pb facs="tcp:20972:50"/> him alſo ſeed to ſow his ground againe, &amp; ſo doth he from yeere to yeere: ſo he that doth as it were ſowe his money vpon the poore, the Lord doth not onely giue him wherewithall to maintaine his family, but he giueth him alſo to ſow vpon the poore from yeere to yeere, he giueth him ability and alſo minde to doe it, for to him that hath ſhall be giuen. On the other ſide, he that is miſerable continueth miſerable ſtill, though he hath neuer a child and knowes not for whome he gathereth his money: yet he hath no heart to beſtowe any thing, god will not honour him with any ſuch honourable ſeruice. 11 This hauing of an heart to beſtowe his goodes, is the thing that deſerueth the name of riches, as Chriſt teacheth vs, Luk. 16. 12. For as an owner is worthy to be accounted more welthy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a little farmer that is tenant at will or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life; ſo is it in this caſe, for theſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches a man carrieth to the graue with him, Rev. 14. 13. and God in mercy will reward them with an euerlaſting reward. But of the other riches, it is ſaid, naked came I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:20972:50"/> to this world, and naked ſhall I goe out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. He doth ſtire them vp to bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by the bleſſed fruite, and from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable effect thereof; for it cauſeth euen the moſt excellent duty, euen the duty of thankſgiuing vnto God, which duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is repeated in the next verſe, I will therefore then ſpeake of it. In the meane time we are not to omit it, that he ſaith it cauſeth thankſgiuing through vs, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through the miniſtrie of the goſpell: if it ſhould be beſtowed vpon a profane people, where by reaſon of their vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe god ſhould haue had no honour by them, this might wel haue cooled their affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from giuing: for without the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell men are vnthankefull, Luk. 6. 35. they ſwallowe vp the bleſsings of god without ſence. But if reliefe be beſtowed where the goſpell is, then god ſhall not looſe his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: for your releife through vs cauſeth thankſgiuing vnto god, ſaith the Apoſtle. If releife be beſtowed vpon rogues and vagabonds, god can haue no ſuch honour by it; but when releife is beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20972:51"/> haue bene taught, that the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men are comforted are as it were the handes of god wherby he conueieth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment vnto them, then god ſhall haue honour.</p>
            <q>
               <p>12 <hi>For the miniſtration of this ſeruice, not onely ſupplieth the necesſities of the Saints, But alſo is aboundant by the thankſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giuing of many vnto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>13 <hi>Which by the experiment of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, praiſe god for your voluntary ſubmiſsion to the goſpell of Chriſt, and for your liberall distribution to them, and to all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>14 <hi>And by their praier for you, deſiring after you greatly for the aboundant grace of God in you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>15 <hi>Thankes therefore be vnto God for his vnſpeakeably gift.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>He commendeth gîuing of releife, firſt becauſe their neceſsities are releiued, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe thereby alſo god is glorified. But before we ſpeake of either of theſe, we are to conſider of this word ſeruice; the word doth indifferently ſignifie any ſacrifice that
<pb facs="tcp:20972:51"/> is offered vnto god or any publike office that a man is called vnto. But becauſe the drift of the Apoſtle is to ſtirre vp vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, we are to take it in the firſt ſence, for that is fitter for this purpoſe then is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: eſpecially ſeeing this tearme, a worde I meane of the like ſignification is vſed to ſet out the excellency of releife, Hebr. 13. 16. Act. 10. 4. Leaſt the baſenes of the parties vpon whome we are exerciſed in giuing of almes ſhould hinder this duty, we are told that in this duty we are attennding v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the perſon of god himſelf, in the doing thereof we doe as it were offer ſacrifices vnto god himſelfe. In a family euery man is deſirous to be imployed about thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that concerne the maſter or the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres her ſelfe, as to be their chamber ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, to attend vpon them there: but to be further remooued from them, and to be occupied in duties in out-houſes where they ſhall ſeldome ſee their maſter, though theſe ſeruices belong to the ſeruing of their maſter, yet being out of their maſters ſight they think that they are out of their mind:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20972:52"/> and therefore they had rather chooſe the former ſeruices that were ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of before rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other. The Apoſtle therfore tels vs that the giuing of almes is the beſt kinde of ſeruice that a man can deuiſe. Chriſt calls thoſe the great commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that concerne god himſelfe, and the other that concernes men are like vnto them. This therefore in ſome ſence being one of thoſe great commaundements, the Lord in mercy muſt needs giue a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward therevnto; it is ſaide that releife ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth the neceſsities of god his ſeruants: men it may be had rather do duty to thoſe that haue not ſuch neede of their helpe, but this kinde of ſeruice is more acceptable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, for it is a better proofe and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſound loue, then that ſeruice is which is imploied about thoſe that be rich: and ſo by conſequence the lord muſt needs like better of the one then of the other. It is a common ſaying, that true loue doth deſcend and not aſcend; and therefore it is obſerued that the grandfather or the father doth loue the child or the nephew, better
<pb facs="tcp:20972:52"/> then the childe or the nephewe doth loue the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfather or the father. In giuing we muſt haue reſpect to the neceſsities of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is a thing not ſo wel thought vpon, whereof it commeth to paſſe that men wil haue much ſpeach about the prouiſion for ſome, but about the prouiſion for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will haue no ſpeach at all though their neceſsitie be much greater. To hane reſpect vnto the neceſsities of men in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, is much more acceptable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to giue hand ouer head: &amp; therfore if men would ſit downe and inquire and take the names of ſuch as ſtand in neede of helpe, in the places where they dwell, to conſider of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordingly: this though it be troubleſome yet it is a great deale more acceptable then penny or two-pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny doole. For the thinge which a man muſt aime at in giuing, is to diſtribute to the neceſsities of the Saints, Rom. 12. 13. Act. 2. 45. For men muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the poore in their kinde, as they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the rich in their kinde. And as to giue the more honour to him which is leſſe honorable, can not be done without offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20972:53"/> wrong to the more honorable perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So to honor thoſe poore ſaints that haue moſt neede with the les releife, can not be doone without offeringe contempt vnto them. The other good that comes by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is thankſgiuing vnto god, we muſt be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful vnto the means as the ſcripture techeth vs, Kings 8. 66. Rom 16. 4. But the lord muſt be the centure and the reſtinge place of our thanks, this thankfulnes is ſaid to be better then any ſacrifiſe pſal 50. we are much called vpon for it, as pſal 107. the paſſeouer, the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſupper, were of purpoſe ordeined to ſtir vs vp to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. The cauſe wherfore the forbidding of meats is acounted the doctrine of diuils, is becauſe it taketh away occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. 1. Timo 4. 3. The thing wherby the ſeruants of god haue mooued the lord to looke mercifully vpon them in their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hath bene the vowing of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The thing which hath troubled the godly in their troubles and griefes hath beene this; namely, that the duty of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe hath then beene greately dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:20972:53"/> Ioel, 1. 13. Seeing therefore that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent duty is procured by giuing releife, this ſhould be a notable motion to make vs forward this waies: and he doth amplify the matter when he ſaith that thanks ſhall be giuen by many. Many knowing the hardneſſe of thoſe times, no doubt prayed vnto God to open the hearts of men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their poore brethren: and when they heard that God had opened mens hearts they could not chooſe but be thankefull, 2. Cor. 1. 11. When many ioyne together in the duty of tankefulneſſe, it makes thoſe which doe giue thankes, to be more ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that duty: euen as many ſtickes beeing laid vpon the fire makes the flame the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter; and the Lord loueth feruent praier and feruent thankefulneſſe, Iam. 5. 16. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a King conſiſteth in the multitude of ſubiects; ſo doth the honour of God conſiſt in the multitude oſ thoſe which are truely thankefull vnto him.</p>
            <p>13 They will praiſe God not onely for their maintenance and releife but becauſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20972:54"/> that thereby they teſtifie their true ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Goſpel, as chap. 8. 5. for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel came from the Iewes whome they were to relieue: for we read, Act. 8. 4. that by the perſecution of Steven thoſe that kept altogether at Ieruſalem before, were now ſcattered, and preached the word e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where amongſt the Gentiles, in ſo much that it is alleadged as a reaſon by the Apoſtle: wherefore he would haue the Gentiles contribute to Ieruſalem, becauſe the Law came out of Sion. If the Gentiles be made partakers of their ſpiritual things, their dutie is alſo to miniſter vnto them in carnall things, Rom. 15. 27. ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. We of the Gentiles were wild oliues, and therefore were to be planted into the naturall oliue before we could thriue. It is ſaid Zachar. 8. 23. that tenne men of all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages of the nations, ſhall take hold of the skirt of him that is a Iew, and ſay we will goe with you, for we haue heard that God is with you: ſo that we ſee that the thanks that God ſhould haue by this, ſhould not be onely for relieuing of them, but for a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20972:54"/> and a more excellent conſideration. So that we are taught hereby, eſpecially ſuch of vs as are miniſters of the word of God, wherefore and for what cauſe we ſhould eſpecially reioyce when God mooues his people to haue any comfortable conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vs, namely not ſo much becauſe our bodies receiues ſome refreſhing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as it is an argument that they haue felt ſweetnes and comfort in our miniſterie, this ſhould make vs triumph for ioy, for it makes the Angels in heauen to reioyce, Luk. 15. as it did alſo the people of the Iewes, Act. 11. They did profeſſe the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel before, but this that the Apoſtle here ſpeakes of was an argument that it was the goſpel I meane with much power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. In that the Apoſtle doth ſo much commend the [voluntarie] ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mans ſelfe to the truth, it is a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion with ſome whether men are to be forced to the exerciſes of religion: but it is plaine that they are to be forced thereunto by ſuch as haue authoritie. For though the Lord doth not like of that mans ſeruice
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20972:55"/> that commeth to the place where his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth with a conſtreyned minde, yet he liketh well of the ſeruice of the magiſtrates in this forme of duty, which is ſo willing to haue others be brought to religion that he forceth them therevnto when they will not be otherwiſe allured: and euen thoſe that at the firſt are drawne by violence to heare the word of God, in continuance of time will come willingly therevnto: for it is onely the word of god which muſt procure an appetite. <hi>No man commeth vnto me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>except my father araweth him.</hi> And there is none of vs which doe now moſt willingly ſubmit our ſelues vnto the goſpell, but at the firſt we came to heare it of cuſtome, becauſe others did ſo, or for noueltie, or for ſome other ſuch reſpect: and we may hope ſo, becauſe the Lord hath promiſed a bleſsing to correction. <hi>Correct the ſcorner,</hi> ſath Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, <hi>and the fooliſh will take heede, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten this child for there is hope.</hi> But as for theſe men their giuing was an argument or manifeſt ſhewe of their voluntary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb facs="tcp:20972:55"/> of themſelues to the Goſpell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this releife was to be gathered by the conſent or agreement of all churches, chap. 8. 24. The reaſons which haue beene alleadged to bring men by force vnto the goſpel, may ſerue alſo to prooue the like inforcement for releife, if otherwiſe men will not be brought or incouraged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. 14 If we would but conſider that the Lord hath put a bleſsing into the handes of diſtreſſed perſons, to beſtowe vpon ſuch as doe releeue them, Iob, 29. 13. then men would ſoone be brought to giue to the poore that they may pray for them, Ezra, 6. 10. It was the thing which made Darius ſo bountifull, that they might pray for the kings life &amp; for the life of his ſonne. This releife ſhall make all good men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after them greately, which may be a very cheereful and comfortable aſſurance vnto vs that god himſelfe doth regard vs, when the ſeruants of god doth long after vs. As the Lord of Hoaſtes liueth, ſaith Eliſha vnto Ahab, in whoſe ſight
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20972:56"/> ſight I ſtand; If it were not that I regarde the preſence of Iehoſaphat the king of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, I would not haue looked towards thee nor ſeene thee. It is a great fauour to haue ſuch a one ſpeake a good word for vs, to whoſe ſpeech the prince wil moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harken: but the poore beeing ſuch as God hath promiſed to giue the hearing vnto, it is therefore a greater benefit then we take it to be, to haue them pray for vs. Thoſe which reſerue all their gifts vntill after their death, doe neither giue any te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony that they truſt not in vncertaine riches but in the liuing Lord, neither haue they this benefit of prayer which is is here ſpoken of: for to what purpoſe ſhould men pray for them at ſuch time when praier will do them no good. As this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of praier ſhould ſet more a worke at all times to be bountifull, ſo when men are viſited with ſickneſſe or any other greate trouble, the hope of finding releife there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhould ſet them aworke to be bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for the Lord hath promiſed mercie to the mercifull. 15 The Apoſtle beeing
<pb facs="tcp:20972:56"/> perſwaded that he ſhould not looſe his wordes, as if the thing which he perſwads them vnto had beene already done, he breaketh forth into thankſgiuing for it: &amp; leaſt any ſhould thinke that he had ſpoken as much for releife as can poſsibly be ſaide or conceiued: he ſaith that is an vnſpekable gift of God, and none of his ordinarie gifts to releiue the poore Saints of god: the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows ſhewed the garments for the poore which Dorcas had made, and that not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her death, but whileſt ſhee was aliue with them, Act. 9. 39. thinking that if any thing would be a meanes to cauſe Peter to lift vp feruent grones vnto the Lord, as he might reſtore her to them againe, that would doe it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
